Chapter 16. The ship.
In bed we concocted our plans for the tomorrow. But to my surprise, and no
small concern, Quiquake now gave me to understand that he had been diligently
consulting Yojo, the name of his black little god, and Yojo had told him two or
three times over, and strongly insisted upon it every way, that instead of our
going together among the wailing fleet in the harbor, and in concert selecting
our craft, instead of this, I say, Yojo earnestly enjoined that the selection of
the ship should rest wholly with me in In as much as Yojo proposed befriending
us, and in order to do so, had already pitched upon a vessel which, if left to
myself, I, Ishmael, should infallibly light upon for all the world, as though
it had turned out by chance, and in that vessel I must immediately ship myself
for the present, irrespective of Quiqu.
I have forgotten to mention that in many things Quiquang placed great confidence
in the excellence of Yojo's judgment and surprising forecast of things and
cherished Yojo with considerable esteem as a rather good sort of god who perhaps
meant well enough upon the whole but in all cases did not succeed in his
benevolent designs. Now this plan of quiques, or rather yojos touching the
selection of our craft, I did not like that plan at all. I had not a little
relied upon Quiquake's sagacity to point out the wher best fitted to carry us and
our fortunes securely. But as all my remmonstrances produced no effect upon
Quiquake, I was obliged to acquies, and accordingly prepared to set about this
business with a determined, rushing sort of energy and vigor that should quickly
settle that trifling little affair. Next morning, early leaving Quiquake, shut up
with Yojo in our little bedroom, for it seemed that it was some sort of Lent or
Ramadan or day of fasting, humiliation, and prayer with Quiquake and Yojo that
day. How it was, I never could find out, for though I applied myself to it
several times, I never could master his liturgies and 39 articles. Leaving
Quequake, then fasting on his tomahawk pipe, and Yojo warming himself at his
sacrificial fire of shavings, I sied out among the shipping. After much prolonged
sauntering and many random inquiries, I learned that there were three ships up
for 3 years voyages, the Devil Dam, the Titbit, and the Peekquad. Devil Dam, I
do not know the origin of Tit.
Peekquad, you will no doubt remember, was the name of a celebrated tribe of
Massachusetts Indians, now extinct as the ancient Mes. I peered in pride about
the Devil Dam. From her, hopped over to the Tit and finally, going on board the
Peekquad, looked around her for a moment, and then decided that this was the very ship for us.
You may have seen many acquaint craft in your day, for all I know. square toaded
luggers, mountainous Japanese junks, butterbox galliots, and whatnot. But
take my word for it, you never saw such a rare old craft as this same rare old
Peekquad. She was a ship of the old school, rather small if anything, with
an old-fashioned claw-footed look about her, long seasoned and weather stained
in typhoons and calms of all four oceans. Her old hull's complexion was
darkened like a French grenaders who has alike fought in Egypt and Siberia. Her
venerable boughs looked bearded. Her mass cut somewhere on the coasts of
Japan where her original ones were lost overboard in a gale. Her mass stood
stiffly up like the spines of the three old kings of Cologne. Her ancient decks
were worn and wrinkled like the pilgrim worshiped flag stone in Canterbury
Cathedral where Beckett bled. But to all these her old antiquities were added new
and marvelous features pertaining to the wild business that for more than half a
century she had followed. Old Captain Pelleg, many years her chief mate before
he commanded another vessel of his own, and now a retired seaman and one of the
principal owners of the Peekquad. This old Pelleg, during the term of his chief
mateship, had built upon her original grotesqueness, and inlaid it all over,
with acquaintness both of material and device, unmatched by anything except it
be Thorill Hakes carved buckler or bedstead. She was apparic
Ethiopian emperor, his neck heavy with pendants of polished ivory. She was a
thing of trophies, a cannibal of a craft. tricking herself forth in the
chased bones of her enemies. All round her unpanled open bull works were
garnished like one continuous jaw with the long sharp teeth of the sperm whale
inserted there for pins to fasten her old hemp and thus and tendons too. Those
thus ran not through base blocks of landwood, but deafly traveled over sheav
of sea ivory. Scorning a turnstyle wheel at her reverend helm, she sported there
a tiller, and that tiller was in one mass, curiously car from the long,
narrow, lowered jaw of her hereditary foe. The helmsman, who steered by that
tiller in a tempest, felt like the tartar when he holds back his fiery
steed by clutching its jaw. A noble craft, but somehow a most melancholy.
All noble things are touched with that.
Now, when I looked about the quarter deck for someone having authority in
order to propose myself as a candidate for the voyage, at first I saw nobody,
but I could not well overlook a strange sort of tent, or rather wigwam, pitched
a little behind the main mass. It seemed only a temporary erection used in port.
It was of a conicle shape some 10 ft high, consisting of the long huge slabs
of limber black bone taken from the middle and highest part of the jaws of
the right whale, planted with their broad ends on the deck, a circle of
these slabs laced together, mutually sloped towards each other, and at the
apex united in a tufted point where the loose hairy fibers waved to and fro like
the top knot on some old Pawatami Sichchum's head. A triangular opening
faced towards the boughs of the ship, so that the insider commanded a complete view forward.
And half concealed in this queer tenement, I at length found one who, by
his seemed to have authority, and who, it being noon, and the ship's work
suspended, was now enjoying respit from the burden of command. He was seated on
an old-fashioned oak chair, wriggling all over with curious carving, and the
bottom of which was formed of a stout interlacing of the same elastic stuff of
which the wigwam was constructed.
There was nothing so very particular perhaps about the appearance of the
elderly man I saw. He was brown and brrawy like most old seaman and heavily
rolled up in blue pilot cloth cut in the Quaker style. Only there was a fine and
almost microscopic network of the minutest wrinkles interlacing round his
eyes which must have arisen from his continual sailings and many hard gales
and always looking to windward. For this causes the muscles about the eyes to
become pursed together. Such eye wrinkles are very effectual in a scowl.
Is this the captain of the Peekquad?
said I, advancing to the door of the tent. Supposing it be the captain of the
Peekquad. What does thou want of him? He demanded. I was thinking of shipping.
Thou was thou. I see thou art no antitrer. Ever been in a stove boat? No,
sir, I never have.
Thus know nothing at all about whailing, I dare say. Eh, nothing, sir, but I have
no doubt I soon shall learn. I've been several voyages in the merchant service,
and I think that merchant service be damned. Talk not that lingo to me. Dust
see that leg? I'll take that leg away from thy stern, if ever thou talkest of
the merchant service to me again.
Marchant service indeed. I suppose now you feel considerable proud of having
served in those marching ships. But flukes man, what makes thee want to go
away then? Eh, it looks a little suspicious, don't it? Eh, hast not been
a pirate, hast thou did not rob thy last captain? Dit thou did not think of
murdering the officers when thou getest to see?
I protested my innocence of these things. I saw that under the mask of
these halfhumorous innuendos, this old seaman as an insulated Quakerish
Nantucketer, was full of his insular prejudices, and rather distrustful of
all aliens, unless they hailed from Cape Cod or the vineyard. But what takes thee
a whailing? I want to know that before I think of shipping ye. Well, sir, I want
to see what whailing is. I want to see the world. Want to see what whaling is?
Eh, have you clapped an eye on Captain Ahab? Who is Captain Ahab, sir? I I I
thought so. Captain Ahab is the captain of this ship. I am mistaken then. I
thought I was speaking to the captain himself.
Thou art speaking to Captain Pelleg.
That's who you're speaking to, young man. It belongs to me and Captain Bildad
to see the Peekquad fitted out for the voyage and supplied with all her needs,
including crew. We are part owners and agents. But as I was going to say, if
thou want us to know what whailing is, as thou tellest you do, I can put you in
the way of finding it out before you bind yourself to it past backing out.
Clap eye on Captain Ahab, young man, and thou will find that he has only one leg.
What do you mean, sir? Was the other lost by a whale? Lost by a whale? Young
man, come nearer to me.
It was devoured, chewed up, crunched by the monstrousest pararmetti that ever chipped a boat.
Ah, I was a little alarmed by his energy, perhaps also a little touched at the
hearty grief in his concluding exclamation, but said as calmly as I
could, "What you say is no doubt true enough, sir. But how could I know there
was any peculiar ferocity in that particular whale, though indeed I might
have inferred as much from the simple fact of the accident?"
Now look you young man, thy lungs are a sort of a soft, do you see? Thou does
not talk shark a bit. Sure you've been to sea before now. Sure of that, sir,
said I. I thought I told you that I had been four voyages in the merchant. Hard
down on that. Mind what I said about the merchant service? Don't aggravate me. I
won't have it. But let us understand each other. I have given thee a hint
about what wailing is. Do you yet feel inclined for it? I do, sir. Very good.
Now, art thou the man to pitch a harpoon down a live whale's throat, and then
jump after it. Answer quick. I am, sir, if it should be positively indispensable
to do so, not to be got rid of, that is,
which I don't take to be the fact. Good again. Now then, thou not only want us
to go whailing to find out by experience what whailing is, but you also want to
go in order to see the world. Was that not what you said? I thought so. Well,
then just step forward there and take a peep over the weather bow and then back
to me and tell me what you see there.
For a moment I stood a little puzzled by this curious request, not knowing
exactly how to take it, whether humorously or in earnest, but
concentrating all his crows feet into one skull, Captain Pelleg started me on
the errand. Going forward and glancing over the weather bow, I perceived that
the ship swinging to her anchor with the flood tide was now oblquely pointing
towards the open ocean. The prospect was unlimited, but exceedingly monotonous
and forbidding. Not the slightest variety that I could see.
Well, what's the report? said Pelleg when I came back. What did you see? Not
much, I replied. Nothing but water.
Considerable horizon, though, and there's a squall coming up, I think.
Well, what does thou think then of seeing the world? Do you wish to go
around Cape Horn to see any more of it?
Eh, can't you see the world where you stand?
I was a little staggered, but go aailing I must, and I would, and the Peekquad
was as good a ship as any, I thought the best, and all this I now repeated to
Pelleg. Seeing me so determined, he expressed his willingness to ship me.
And thou mayest as well sign the papers right off, he added. Come along with,
and so saying, he led the way below deck into the cabin.
Seated on the transom was what seemed to me a most uncommon and surprising
figure. It turned out to be Captain Bildad, who along with Captain Pelleg
was one of the largest owners of the vessel. The other shares, as is
sometimes the case in these ports, being held by a crowd of old annuitants,
widows, fatherless children, and chancery wards, each owning about the
value of a timber head or a foot of plank or a nail or two in the ship.
People in Nantucket invest their money in whailing vessels the same way that
you do yours in approved state stocks bringing in good interest. Now, Bildad,
like Pelleg and indeed many other Nantucketers, was a Quaker, the island
having been originally settled by that sect, and to this day its inhabitants in
general retain in an uncommon measure the peculiarities of the Quaker, only
variously and anomalously modified by things altogether alien and heterogeneous,
for some of these same Quakers are the most sanguinary of all sailors and whale
hunters. They are fighting Quakers. They are Quakers with a vengeance.
So that there are instances among them of men who named with scripture names, a
singularly common fashion on the island, and in childhood naturally embibing the
stately dramatic the thou of the Quaker idiom, still from the audacious, daring,
and boundless adventure of their subsequent lives, strangely blend with
these unoutgrown peculiarities. a thousand bold dashes of character not
unworthy of a Scandinavian sea king or a poetical pagan Roman. And when these
things unite in a man of greatly superior natural force, with a globular
brain and a ponderous heart, who has also by the stillness and seclusion of
many long night watches in the remotest waters, and beneath constellations never
seen here at the north, been led to think untraditionally and independently,
receiving all nature's sweet or savage impressions fresh from her own virgin,
voluntary and confiding breast, and thereby chiefly, but with some help from
accidental advantages to learn a bold and nervous lofty language. That man
makes one in a whole nation senses, a mighty pageant creature formed for noble
tragedies. Nor will it at all detract from him dramatically regarded, if
either by birth or other circumstances, he have what seems a half-willful
overruling morbidness at the bottom of his nature. For all men tragically great
are made so through a certain morbidness. Be sure of this, oh young
ambition. All mortal greatness is but disease. But as yet we have not to do
with such a one, but with quite another, and still a man who, if indeed peculiar,
it only results again from another phase of the Quaker modified by individual circumstances.
Like Captain Pelleg, Captain Bildad was a wellto-do retired whaleman. But unlike
Captain Pelleg, who cared not a rush for what are called serious things, and
indeed deemed those self-same serious things the variest of all trifles,
Captain Bildad had not only been originally educated according to the
strictest sect of Nantucket Quakerism, but all his subsequent ocean life and
the sight of many unclad creatures round the horn, all that had
not moved this nativeborn Quaker one single jot, had not so much as altered
one angle of his vest. Still, for all this immutableness, there was some lack
of common consistency about the worthy Captain Bildad. Though refusing from
conscientious scruples to bear arms against land invaders, yet himself had
illimitably invaded the Atlantic and Pacific, and though a sworn foe to human
bloodshed, yet had he in his straightbodied coat spilled tons upon
tons of Leviathan gore. How now, in the contemplative evening of his days, the
pious Bildad reconciled these things in his reminiscence, I do not know, but it
did not seem to concern him much, and very probably he had long since come to
the sage and sensible conclusion that a man's religion is one thing, and this
practical world quite another. This world pays dividends, rising from a
little cabin boy in short clothes of the drabus drab to a harpooner in the broad
shadbellied waste coat. From that becoming boat header, chief mate and
captain, and finally a ship owner, Billad, as I hinted before, had
concluded his adventurous career by wholly retiring from active life at the
goodly age of 60 and dedicating his remaining days to the quiet receiving of
his well-earned income.
Now, Bildad, I am sorry to say, had the reputation of being an encouraable old
hunks, and in his seagoing days, a bitter, hard taskmaster. They told me in
Nantucket, though it certainly seems a curious story, that when he sailed the
old Katagut whaleman, his crew, upon arriving home, were mostly all carried
ashore to the hospital, sore, exhausted, and worn out. For a pious man,
especially for a Quaker, he was certainly rather hard-hearted, to say
the least. He never used to swear though at his men, they said, but somehow he
got an inordinate quantity of cruel, unmitigated hard work out of them. When
Bildad was a chief mate, to have his drabcoled eye intently looking at you
made you feel completely nervous, till you could clutch something, a hammer or
a marlin spike, and go to work like mad at something or other, never mind what.
Indolence and idleness perished before him. His own person was the exact
embodiment of his utilitarian character.
On his long gaunt body he carried no spare flesh, no superfluous beard, his
chin having a soft economical nap to it, like the worn nap of his broadbrimmed hat.
Such then was the person that I saw seated on the transom when I followed
Captain Pelleg down into the cabin. The space between the decks was small, and
there bolt upright sat old Billad, who always sat so, and never leaned, and
this to save his coattails. His broad brim was placed beside him. His legs
were stiffly crossed, his drab vesture was buttoned up to his chin, and
spectacles on nose he seemed absorbed in reading from a ponderous volume. "Bild!"
cried Captain Pelleg. At it again, Billad, eh, you've been studying those
scriptures now for the last 30 years, to my certain knowledge. How far you get, Bildad?
As if long habituated to such profane talk from his old shipmate, Bildad,
without noticing his present irreverence, quietly looked up, and
seeing me, glanced again inquiringly towards Pelleg. He says he's our man,
Bildad, said Pelleg. He wants to ship.
Dust thee, said Bildad in a hollow tone, and turning round to me. I dust, said I,
unconsciously. He was so intense a Quaker.
What do you think of him, Billad? said Pelleg.
He'll do, said Billad, eyeing me, and then went on spelling away at his book
in a mumbling tone quite audible.
I thought him the queerest old Quaker I ever saw, especially as Pelleg, his
friend and old shipmate, seemed such a bluster, but I said nothing, only
looking round me sharply. Pelleg now threw open a chest, and drawing forth
the ship's articles, placed pen and ink before him, and seated himself at a
little table. I began to think it was high time to settle with myself at what
terms I would be willing to engage for the voyage. I was already aware that in
the whailing business they paid no wages, but all hands, including the
captain, received certain shares of the profit, called lays, and that these lays
were proportioned to the degree of importance pertaining to the respective
duties of the ship's company. I was also aware that being a greenhand at
whailing, my own lay could not be very large. But considering that I was used
to the sea, could steer a ship, splice a rope, and all that, I made no doubt that
from all I had heard, I should be offered at least the 275th lay, that is,
the 275th part of the clear net proceeds of the voyage, whatever that might
eventually amount to. And though the 275th lay was what they call a rather
long lay, yet it was better than nothing, and if we had a lucky voyage,
might pretty nearly pay for the clothing I would wear out on it, not to speak of
my 3 years beef and board for which I would not have to pay one styiver.
It might be thought that this was a very poor way to accumulate a princely
fortune, and so it was a very poor way indeed. But I am one of those that never
take on about princely fortunes and am quite content if the world is ready to
board and lodge me while I am putting up at this grim sign of the thundercloud.
Upon the whole I thought that the 275th lay would be about the fair thing. But I
would not have been surprised if I had been offered the 200th considering I was
of a broad shouldered make.
But one thing, nevertheless, that made me a little distrustful about receiving
a generous share of the profits was this. Assure I had heard something of
both Captain Pelleg and his unaccountable old crony Billad, how that
they, being the principal proprietors of the Peekquad, therefore the other and
more inconsiderable scattered owners left nearly the whole management of the
ship's affairs to these two. And I did not know but what the stingy old Billad
might have a mighty deal to say about shipping hands, especially as I now
found him on board the Peekquad, quite ated home there in the cabin, and
reading his Bible as if at his own fireside.
Now, while Pelleg was vainly trying to mend a pen with his jack knife, old
Bildad, to my no small surprise, considering that he was such an
interested party in these proceedings, Bildad never heeded us, but went on
mumbling to himself out of his book, "Lay not up for yourselves treasures
upon earth, where m" Well, Captain Bildad, interrupted Pelleg. What do you
say? What lay shall we give this young man?
Thou knowest best, was the sephilcrol reply. The 777th wouldn't be too much, would it? Where
moth and rust do corrupt. But lay lay indeed, thought I, and such a lay. The 777th.
Well, old Bildad, you are determined that I, for one, shall not lay up many
lays here below, where moth and rust do corrupt. It was an exceedingly long lay
that indeed. And though from the magnitude of the figure it might at
first deceive the landsmen, yet the slightest consideration will show that
though 777 is a pretty large number, yet when you come to make a tenth of it, you
will see as I say that the 777th part of
a farthing is a good deal less than 777 gold dloons. And so thought I at the
time. I blast your eyes, Billad, cried Pelleg. Thou does not want to swindle
this young man. He must have more than that.
777th again, said Billad without lifting his eyes, and then went on mumbling. For
where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. I am going to put him
down for the 300th, said Pelleg. Do you hear that, Bildad? The 300th lay, I say.
Bildad laid down his book, and turning solemnly towards him, said, "Captain
Pelleg, thou hast a generous heart, but thou must consider the duty thou owe us
to the other owners of this ship, widows and orphans, many of them, and that if
we too abundantly reward the labors of this young man, we may be taking bread
from those widows and those orphans."
The 777th lay, Captain Pelleg. Thou, Bildad, roared Pelleg, starting up and
clattering about the cabin. Last year, Captain Bildad, if I had followed thy
advice in these matters, I would have for now had a conscience to lug about,
and would be heavy enough to founder the largest ship that ever sailed round Cape Horn.
Captain Pelleg said Bildad steadily. Thy conscience may be drawing 10 in of water
or 10 fathoms, I can't tell. But as thou art still an impenitent man, Captain
Pelleg, I greatly fear, lest thy conscience be but a leaky one, and will
in the end sink thee foundering down to the fiery pit, Captain Pelleg. Fiery
pit, fiery pit. You insult me, man. past all natural bearing. You insult me. It's
an allfired outrage to tell any human creature that he's bound to hell. Fluks
and flames. Bildad. Say that again to me and start my soul bolts. I'll I'll Yes,
I'll swallow a live goat with all his hair and horns on. Out of the cabin, ye
caning drabcoled son of a wooden gun. A straight wake with ye.
As he thundered out this, he made a rush at Bildad, but with a marvelous oblique
sliding solarity, Bildad for that time eluded him. Alarmed at this terrible
outburst between the two principal and responsible owners of the ship, and
feeling half a mind to give up all idea of sailing in a vessel so questionably
owned, and temporarily commanded, I stepped aside from the door to give
egress to Bildad, who I made no doubt was all eagerness to vanish before the
awakened wrath of Pelleg. But to my astonishment he sat down again on the
transom very quietly and seemed to have not the slightest intention of
withdrawing. He seemed quite used to the impenitent Pelleg in his ways. As for
Pelleg, after letting off his rage as he had, there seemed no more left in him,
and he too sat down like a lamb, though he twitched a little as if still nervously agitated.
He whistled at last. A squall's gone off to lure it, I think.
Bildad, thou used to be good at sharpening a lance. Mend that pen, will
you? My jack knife here needs the grindstoneone. That's he. Thank you,
Bildad. Now then, my young man, Ishmael is thy name, didn't you say? Well, then
down you go here, Ishmail, for the 300th lay. Captain Pelleg, said I. I have a
friend with me who wants a ship, too.
Shall I bring him down tomorrow? To be sure, said Pelleg. Fetch him along, and
we'll look at him. What lay does he want? groaned Bildad, glancing up from
the book in which he had again been burying himself.
Ah, never mind about that, Billad said Pelleg. Has he ever wailed at any
turning to me killed more whales than I can count, Captain Pelleg. Well, bring
him along then. And after signing the papers, off I went, nothing doubting but
that I had done a good morning's work, and that the Peekquad was the identical
ship that Yojo had provided to carry Quiquake and me round the Cape. But I
had not proceeded far when I began to be think me that the captain with whom I
was to sail yet remained unseen by me.
Though indeed in many cases a whale ship will be completely fitted out and
receive all her crew on board the captain makes himself visible by
arriving to take command. For sometimes these voyages are so prolonged, and the
shore intervals at home so exceedingly brief, that if the captain have a
family, or any absorbing concernment of that sort, he does not trouble himself
much about his ship in port, but leaves her to the owners till all is ready for
sea. However, it is always as well to have a look at him before irrevocably
committing yourself into his hands.
Turning back, I accosted Captain Pelleg, inquiring where Captain Ahab was to be
found. And what does thou want of Captain Ahab? It's all right enough.
Thou art shipped. Yes, but I should like to see him. But I don't think you wilt
be able to at present. I don't know exactly what's the matter with him, but
he keeps close inside the house. A sort of sick, and yet he don't look so. In
fact, he ain't sick. But no, he isn't well either. Anyhow, young man, he won't
always see me, so I don't suppose he will thee. He's a queer man, Captain
Ahab. So some think, but a good one. Oh, thou like him well enough. No fear, no
fear. He's a grand, ungodly, godlike man, Captain Ahab. Doesn't speak much,
but when he does speak, then you may well listen. Mark, be forewarned. Ahab's
above the common. Ahab's been in colleges, as well as amongst the
cannibals. been used to deeper wonders than the waves. Fixed his fiery lance in
mightier stranger foes than whales. His lance I the keenest and the shest that
out of all our aisle. Oh, he ain't Captain Bildad. No, and he ain't Captain
Pelleg. He's Ahab, boy. And Ahab of old thou knowest was a crowned king and a
very vile one. When that wicked king was slain, the dogs did they not lick his blood?
Come hither to me. Hither. Hither, said Pelleg, with a significance in his eye
that almost startled me. Look ye lad.
Never say that on board the Peekquad.
Never say it anywhere. Captain Ahab did not name himself. It was a foolish,
ignorant whim of his crazy widowed mother who died when he was only 12
month old. And yet the old squa Tistig at Gayhead said that the name would
somehow prove prophetic. and perhaps other fools like her may tell thee the
same. I wish to warn thee, it's a lie. I know Captain Ahab well. I've sailed with
him as mate years ago. I know what he is. A good man. Not a pious good man
like Bildad, but a swearing good man, something like me. Only there's a good
deal more of him. I I I know that he was
never very jolly, and I know that on the passage home he was a little out of his
mind for a spell, but it was the sharp shooting pains in his bleeding stump
that brought that about, as anyone might see. I know, too, that ever since he
lost his leg last voyage by that oursed whale, he's been a kind of moody,
desperate, moody, and savage sometimes.
But that will all pass off. And once for all let me tell thee and assure thee
young man, it's better to sail with a moody good captain than a laughing bad
one. So goodbye to thee, and wrong not Captain Ahab, because he happens to have
a wicked name. Besides, my boy, he has a wife not three voyages wedded, a sweet
resigned girl. Think of that. And by that sweet girl, that old man has a
child. Hold ye then, can there be any utter hopeless harm in Ahab? No. No, my
lad. Stricken, blasted if he be, Ahab has his humanities.
As I walked away, I was full of thoughtfulness. What had been
incidentally revealed to me of Captain Ahab filled me with a certain wild
vagueness of painfulness concerning him, and somehow at the time I felt a
sympathy and a sorrow for him, but for I don't know what, unless it was the cruel
loss of his leg.
And yet I also felt a strange awe of him, but that sort of awe which I cannot
at all describe was not exactly awe. I do not know what it was, but I felt it,
and it did not disincin me towards him, though I felt impatience at what seemed
like mystery in him so imperfectly as he was known to me then. However, my
thoughts were at length carried in other directions, so that for the present dark
Ahab slipped my mind.